Guide to the Brecht Forum and New York Marxist School Records TAM.635
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Brecht Forum and New York Marxist School Records
1960s-2023
1960s-2017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Brecht Forum (New York, N.Y.)
New York Marxist School
Boger, Mary
Birkhold, Matt
TAM.635
59.25 Linear Feet in 58 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 half manuscript box
760 Gigabytes on 4 hard drives and 1 floppy disk
3000 audiocassettes on approximately 3000 cassette tapes
38 videocassettes on 24 VHS and 12 Betacam tapes
2 websites in 2 archived websites.
This collection contains the files of the Brecht Forum and the New York Marxist School. The New York Marxist School, now part of the Brecht Forum, was founded in 1975 to promote the study and renewal of Marxist ideas and their application to contemporary issues. The Brecht Forum offers community based educational programs such as public lectures and seminars, art exhibitions, performances, popular education workshops, and language classes. The collection contains minutes, reports, curricula, catalogs, course syllabi and reading materials, programs, newsletters, Marxist Education Collective documents, materials of the school's Science Task Force; materials about the Grenada revolution and its overthrow; Philadelphia Marxist School materials; topical files, including files on the World Trade Center Trial, and files on several countries. It also contains Brecht Forum newspapers, event flyers, correspondence, photographs, programming files, minutes and reports from the New York Marxist School and Marxist Education Collective, and audio cassette recordings of conference events and lectures.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mary Boger in 2003; additional materials were donated by Matt Birkhold on behalf of Brecht Forum in 2013 and 2014, and found in the repository in 2014. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2003.025, 2013.025, 2014.080, and 2014.127.
https://brechtforum.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Communism, Socialism, Trotskyism Web Archive. In November 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In February 2023, https://www.youtube.com/@brechtforum/videos/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.033.
Appraisal note
Confidential material and a small number of duplicates were removed from this collection.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into two series by organization; Series I: Brecht Forum Records and Series II: Mary Boger New York Marxist School Records. Materials within series are arranged in rough groupings by topic. This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donors.
Historical Note
In 1975, a group of civil rights, community, labor, and student activists came together to found the New York Marxist School, which became part of the larger Brecht Forum, a left political, cultural and educational center in New York City. A leading role was played by Arthur Felberbaum (1935-1979), earlier a Trotskyist activist. The NYMS sought to promote the study and renewal of Marxist ideas and their application to contemporary issues. In 1984, New York Marxist School became incorporated as the Brecht Forum to include a broader range of educational and artistic programs. The New York Marxist School remained the Forum's core project, but also expanded to include additional projects like the Institute for Popular Education, founded in 1990 in collaboration with the Theater of the Oppressed Laboratory & Arts at the Brecht. The Brecht Forum offered programs designed to promote critical analysis of capitalist society through programs such as public lectures and seminars, art exhibitions, performances, popular education workshops, and language classes. Brecht Forum closed in 2014 due to financial difficulties.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Arthur Felberbaum Papers (TAM 319)
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the New York Marxist School (NYMS) and Brecht Forum, a Marxist educational institution based in Brooklyn, New York. Originally established as two organizations, NYMS and Brecht Forum merged in 1985. The collection includes the institutional records of both organizations before and after their incorporation. Brecht Forum records include financial, fundraising and donor materials; Brecht Forum newspapers; flyers for events hosted by Brecht Forum; correspondence; photographs; files related to programming and educational courses; minutes and reports from the New York Marxist School and Marxist Education Collective; audio cassette recordings of conference events and lectures, and four hard drives. New York Marxist School records include early organizational files, meeting minutes, educational and programming files, conference materials, and promotional materials. NYMS remained an educational center after it was incorporated in Brecht Forum, and consequently records from each organization overlap to some degree.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Grenada -- History -- American Invasion, 1983.; Communist education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Marxism -- United States.; Adult education -- New York (State) -- New York; Grenada -- History -- Coup d'etat, 1979.; Marxian economics; Marxism -- History.; Marxist criticism.; Philosophy, Marxist; New York Marxist School; Mestres, Liz; New York Marxist School. Science Task Force; Brecht Forum (New York, N.Y.); Felberbaum, Arthur, 1935-1979; Boger, Mary; Birkhold, Matt
- Series I: Brecht Forum Records, 1960s-2023; 1960s-2017
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records of Brecht Forum (dated 1960s-2014). It includes organizational correspondence, public programming files, course catalogues, fundraising files, meeting minutes, financial records, and newsletters. The series also contains numerous audio recording of conferences, public events, and lectures.
  - Cassette Tapes, 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1980s-2000s (Box 4)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
  - Betacam Tapes (some labeled "Manifestivity," referring to Brecht Forum's 150th anniversary celebration of the Communist Manifesto), circa 1998 (Box 6)
  - Cassette Tapes (original box labeled "BAC 99"), 1990s-2000s (Box 7)
  - Correspondence - A through C, 1980s-2010s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence - C through H, 1980s-2010s (Box 9)
  - Correspondence - H through M, 1980s-2010s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence - M through R, 1980s-2010s (Box 11)
  - Correspondence - R through T, 1980s-2010s (Box 12)
  - Correspondence - U through Z, and Annette Rubenstein Papers and Photographs, 1960s-2010s (Box 13)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1990s-2000s (Box 14)
  - Publicity/Program Calendars and Programming Files re: July Intensive School, 1970s-2010s (Box 15)
  - Programming Files re: July Intensive School and Marxist Education Conferences, 1970s-1990s (Box 16)
  - Programming and Subject Files, 1970s-1990s (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20)
  - Programming Files re: Faculty Meetings, Arts Programming, Brecht Forum History, etc., 1980s-1990s (Box 20, Box 21)
  - Programming and Subject Files, circa 1980-1999 (Box 22, Box 23)
  - Programming and Subject Files, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 24)
  - Programming Files, 1990s-2000s (Box 25)
  - Programming and Fundraising Files, 1990s-2000s (Box 25, Box 26)
  - Fundraising Files, 1990s-2000s (Box 26, Box 27, Box 28)
  - Programming and Fundraising Files, 1970s-1990s (Box 29, Box 30)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1970s-2000s (Box 31)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1980s (Box 32)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1980s-2000s (Box 33)
  - Cassette Tapes, 1970s-1990s (Box 34)
  - New Marxist School - Catalogs, Reports etc., NY Committee on Marxist Education Minutes, Marxist Education Collective- Minutes, Reports etc., 1975-1999 (Box 35, Box 30)
  - Marxist Education Collective - Minutes, Reports etc., NY Marxist School - Minutes Notebook, School Info. etc., Brecht Forum event fliers, 1970-1985 (Box 30, Box 35)
  - School of Marxist Education Course Materials and Event Fliers, 1970s-1992 (Box 35, Box 36)
  - Brecht Forum Newspapers, 1999-2004 (Box 39)
  - Financial and Programming Files, 1980s-2014 (Box 36, Box 37)
  - Fundraising and Programming Files, 1980s-2014 (Box 37, Box 38)
  - Financial and Subject Files, 1980s-2014 (Box 38)
  - Hard Drives, undated (Box 43)
  - Archived Website, October 2007-February 2023; 2 websites in 2 archived websites. (Box Electronic Records)
    Scope and Content Note
    The Brecht Forum, originally located at 451 West Street in Manhattan, now at 388 Atlantic Avenue in Brooklyn, is a Marxist cultural and educational center. The Brecht Forum was founded in 1975 as The New York Marxist School. In 1984, the founding collective incorporated as The Brecht Forum with The New York Marxist School as the Forum's core project. In addition to the New York Marxist School, it also offers other programs, language classes, and arts and cultural events. The website contains information on their curriculum and classes, programming from 2007-2014, as well as economic news analysis. Over the years, the Brecht Forum supported different types of programming, including the Neues Kabarett, the Right to City podcast series, the Manifestoon, the Institute for Popular Education, the Theater of the Oppressed Laboratory, the Harvey Goldberg Classroom Benefits from 2006-2009, Strategic Visions discussion series, and other events and programs. In 2014, after the Brecht Forum closed, the website remained active as a video gallery until 2017. The YouTube channel was focused on the years 2007-2014, the majority of which were uploaded to be part of the video gallery on the main website after the Brecht Forum's closing.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
- Series II: Mary Boger New York Marxist School Records, 1970s-2000s
  The series contains early New York Marxist School records maintained by founding member Mary Boger. It includes NYMS documents; minutes, reports, curricula, catalogs, course syllabi and reading materials, programs, newsletters, public events documents, Marxist Education Collective documents, including conference materials; materials about the Grenada revolution and its overthrow, including tapes and slides; Science Task Force materials; Philadelphia Marxist School materials; topical files (political economy, Russian Revolution, etc.); files on several countries, including Cuba, El Salvador, Portugal, Puerto Rico, etc.; Women's movement materials; cultural magazines; and files on the World Trade Center Trial.
  - Grenada Slides, 1978-1983 (Box 40)
  - Grenada Clippings and Publications, 1980-1984 (Box 44)
  - Grenada, 1980-1984 (Box 45, Box 46)
  - Grenada Audiocassettes, 1981-1983 (Box 41)
  - New York Marxist School Public Event Leaflets and Brochures, 1976-1986 (Box 47)
  - Anti-Colonial and Independence Movements: Puerto Rico, Cuba, El Salvador, Portugal, Africa, and East Timor, 1975-1989 (Box 47, Box 46)
  - Audio Tapes: Puerto Rico/F.M.L.N., 1982 (Box 41)
  - Early Marxist School Documents: Files on Individuals, 1975-1979 (Box 48)
  - Education: Pre-School, "Alternative Summer" School, and Marxist Education Collective, 1975-2001 (Box 48, Box 49)
  - Brecht Forum and New York Marxist School Programs: Event Schedules, Pamphlets, and Flyers, 1997-2001 (Box 49, Box 50)
  - New York Marxist School Newsletters and Course Catalogs, 1979-1991 (Box 50)
  - Marxist Education Collective: Marxist Education Theory and Women's Study Group, 1975-1987 (Box 50, Box 51)
  - Marxist Education Collective and New York Committee for Marxist Education (NYCME): Minutes, Discussion Bulletins, and Programming Committee Files, 1976-1985 (Box 51, Box 52)
  - School for Marxist Education and Marxist Education Collective (MEC): MEC Split and Arthur Felberbaum, circa 1976-1978 (Box 53)
  - Brecht Forum and New York Marxist School: Programs Files, Leaflet, Curriculum, and Schedules, 1983-1999 (Box 54, Box 55)
  - Brecht Forum and New York Marxist School Executive Board Minutes, 1995-2000 (Box 55, Box 56)
  - 150th Anniversary of Communist Manifesto: Conference and Program Files, 1998 (Box 55)
  - Brecht Forum and New York Marxist School: Education Programming on Palestine, the Middle East, and Popular Education, 1983-1993 (Box 56)
  - Cultural Magazines and Studies on Capitalism, 1973-1981 (Box 57, Box 56)
  - Periodicals and Pamphlets: Women's Movement, 1970-1984 (Box 57)
  - Science Task Force: Articles, Working Papers, and Science Classes, 1978-1985 (Box 58)
  - Readings on Imperialism, the America in Question, Race and Class, Money, Debt, the Nature of the USSR, and the Russian Revolution, 1975-1987 (Box 58, Box 59)
  - World Trade Center Trial: Trial Materials, circa 1993-1994 (Box 59, Box 60)
  - World Trade Center Trial: Videocassettes, 1993-1994 (Box 42)